<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A tender visitation of love, to both the Universities Oxford and Cambridge and to the Inns of Court and Chancery even to the seed of God in you all, for you to mind, and consider ere it be too late. From the movings of the Lord, in your friend George Bishop.</title>
            <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210721</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825444</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825444</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29826</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28242)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29826)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2165:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A tender visitation of love, to both the Universities Oxford and Cambridge and to the Inns of Court and Chancery even to the seed of God in you all, for you to mind, and consider ere it be too late. From the movings of the Lord, in your friend George Bishop.</title>
                  <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Robert Wilson, and are to be sold at his shop at the Black-spread Eagle and Windmill in Martins Le Grand and also by Richard Moon book-seller in Wine-Street in Bristol,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With errata at foot of p. 19.</note>
                  <note>Copy stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29826:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Tender Viſitation of Love, To <hi>both</hi> the UNIVERSITIES <hi>OXFORD</hi> and <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> AND To the <hi>Jnns</hi> of <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Chancery</hi> Even to the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>you</hi> All, for <hi>you</hi> to mind, and conſider <hi>ere it be too late.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the <hi>movings</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> in <hi>your</hi> Friend</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>And I ſaid, Hear I pray you, O Heads of <hi>Jacob,</hi> And ye Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is it not for you to know Judgement?</q>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Black-ſpread Eagle</hi> and <hi>Windmill</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand</hi> and alſo by <hi>Richard Moon</hi> Book-Seller in <hi>Wine-Street</hi> in <hi>Briſtol.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:29826:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29826:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Tender</hi> Viſitation of <hi>Love,</hi> to <hi>Both</hi> the <hi>Univerſities Oxford,</hi> and <hi>Cambridg,</hi> and to the <hi>Inns</hi> of <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIENDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is <hi>ſomething</hi> in <hi>you</hi> all <hi>that's Eternal, which</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>God</hi> can ſatisfie, <hi>which</hi> came from <hi>God;</hi> In the <hi>Proſperity</hi> or <hi>Suffering</hi> of <hi>which</hi> ſtands <hi>your Welfare</hi> or <hi>undoing for Ever,</hi> for as much as <hi>God</hi> is <hi>with</hi> or <hi>againſt you, as well</hi> or <hi>ill ye</hi> deal with <hi>it:</hi> And <hi>Gods</hi> being <hi>with</hi> or <hi>againſt you,</hi> is <hi>your bleſſedneſs</hi> or <hi>Everlaſting Deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>this Eternal</hi> thing in <hi>you</hi> all, is the <hi>Soul (God breathed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man the breath of Life, and man became a living Soul, after the Image of God created he him in Righteouſneſſe, and true Holineſſe) which</hi> being in <hi>Death</hi> by <hi>reaſon</hi> of <hi>Corruption</hi> (for, <hi>By one man ſin entered into the World, and Death by Sin; And ſo Death paſſed over all men, for that all have ſinned</hi>) and by <hi>Death</hi> being <hi>held under</hi> or in <hi>Captivity,</hi> by <hi>him</hi> who hath the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Death:</hi> it is made <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> unto <hi>Bondage</hi> (for, <hi>being Servants of ſin, ye are free from Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; And to whom ye yield your ſelves Servants to obey, his Servants ye are to whom ye obey; Whether of ſin unto Death, or of Obedience unto Life: And the wages of ſin is Death, but the gift of God is Eternal Life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord</hi>) and being <hi>held under</hi> or made <hi>ſubject</hi> to <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> it is <hi>ſeparate</hi> from <hi>God, without Chriſt, an Alien from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>A ſtranger from the Covenant of promiſe, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no hope; And without God in the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>all</hi> men <hi>by Nature,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> is <hi>your</hi> ſtate whilſt <hi>ye</hi> know not that <hi>your Redeemer liveth,</hi> and that <hi>your Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er lives ye</hi> know not, whilſt <hi>ye</hi> feel not. <hi>Him living in you;</hi> And <hi>him ye</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:29826:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> feel not <hi>living in you,</hi> whilſt <hi>ye</hi> are in <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>in Death ye are,</hi> whilſt <hi>Death</hi> hath power over <hi>you.</hi> And <hi>Death hath power over you,</hi> whilſt <hi>ye</hi> are <hi>not delivered</hi> from the <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> and from <hi>the fear of Death, ye are not delivered,</hi> whilſt <hi>ye</hi> are <hi>ſubject</hi> to <hi>Bondage</hi> (for <hi>foraſmuch as the Children are partakers of Fleſh and Blood, he alſo him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, likewiſe, took part of the ſame, that through Death he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him that had the power of Death, that is the Devil, and deliver them who through fear of Death, were all their life time, ſubject unto Bondage</hi>) and <hi>ſubject unto Bondage ye</hi> are, whilſt <hi>ſin</hi> hath <hi>dominion</hi> over <hi>you,</hi> (for <hi>of whom a man is overcome, of the ſame is he brought in Bondage</hi>) and, <hi>ſin ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> dominion over you,</hi> whilſt <hi>ye</hi> obey <hi>it</hi> in the <hi>luſts</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and, <hi>ſin having dominion over you, ye</hi> are <hi>under</hi> the <hi>Law:</hi> And whilſt <hi>ye</hi> are <hi>under the Law, ye</hi> are <hi>under</hi> the <hi>curſe.</hi> And being <hi>under the curſe, ye</hi> are (dying ſo) <hi>moſt</hi> miſerable, for, <hi>ſuch</hi> ſhall be <hi>turned into Hell,</hi> and, <hi>out of Hell theres no Redemption:</hi> For, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed, into everlaſting fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> will the <hi>King ſay to them on his left hand, when he ſhall come in his Glory, and all his Holy Angels with him, and ſhall ſit unpo the Throne of his Glory, and theſe ſhall go into everlaſting puniſhment, but the Righteous into Life Eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, it concerns <hi>you,</hi> whilſt <hi>ye</hi> have time, to <hi>mind,</hi> and <hi>conſider, ere it be too late,</hi> the <hi>things</hi> that appertain to <hi>your</hi> Eternal peace; That ſo <hi>it</hi> may be <hi>well</hi> with <hi>that</hi> in <hi>every</hi> one of <hi>you,</hi> in the <hi>welfare</hi> of <hi>which</hi> doth ſtand <hi>your</hi> Bleſſedneſſe and Proſperity for <hi>ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now unto <hi>this</hi> there is no <hi>other</hi> way than <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Light, the Light of the World,</hi> the <hi>true Light that lighteh every man that cometh into the World, in whom was life, and the life, was the Light of men:</hi> Who, <hi>was in the beginning with God, who was God,</hi> by whom <hi>all things were made, and without</hi> whom <hi>was not any thing made that was made? The Word, the Word of God; The Word nigh you, in your mouth, and in your heart, which Moſes</hi> ſpake of ſaying, <hi>This Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> (viz. <hi>the Book of the Law) which I command thee this Day, It is not hidden from thee, nor is it far off; It is not in Heaven, that thou ſhouldſt ſay, who ſhall go up for us into Heaven, and bring it to us, that we may hear it, and do it? Neither is it beyond the Sea, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay, who ſhall go over the Sea, and bring it to us, that we may hear it and do it? But the Word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayeſt do it.</hi> And <hi>which Paul</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29826:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> Preached when <hi>he</hi> ſaid, <hi>the Righteouſneſſe which is of Faith, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on this wiſe, ſay not in thine heart, who ſhall aſcend into Heaven? (that is to bring Chriſt down from above</hi>) or, <hi>who ſhall deſcend into the deep? (That is, to bring up Chriſt again from the dead</hi>) but, <hi>what ſaith it? The Word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that is the Word of Faith,</hi> which <hi>we Preach; Whoſe</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> was, <hi>to open their eyes, and to turn them from darkneſse to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God, that they may receive forgiveneſſe of ſins, and inheritance among them that are Sanctified by Faith,</hi> which <hi>is in me;</hi> And for <hi>this</hi> was <hi>he</hi> ſent, by <hi>him</hi> who is the <hi>Son of God (who</hi> met <hi>him</hi> in the way) the <hi>Saviour</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> the <hi>Covenant of Light to the Gentiles, and the glory of his People of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>this</hi> Chriſt is <hi>in you, except ye be Reprobates:</hi> and the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Chriſt, it is in <hi>you, which</hi> ſhews <hi>you</hi> evil, the <hi>compaſſe</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of <hi>all your</hi> actions, <hi>which</hi> ſearcheth <hi>your</hi> heart, &amp; tryeth <hi>your</hi> reigns, the <hi>candle</hi> of the <hi>Lord, that</hi> ſearcheth the <hi>inward</hi> parts of the <hi>bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> which <hi>ſhines</hi> in <hi>darkneſse,</hi> but the <hi>darkneſſe</hi> comprehends <hi>it</hi> not. And the <hi>Dominion</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Chriſt, it is in <hi>you</hi> (the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>God) which reproves you for ſin (the Comforter, when he is come he ſhall reprove the World of ſin; Now the Lord is that Spirit) who</hi> is the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of <hi>Salvation,</hi> the <hi>Everlaſting Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> the <hi>Rule,</hi> the <hi>meaſure</hi> of <hi>all</hi> things; <hi>That's over</hi> all, <hi>that's above</hi> all, <hi>that comprehends</hi> all; The <hi>Supream,</hi> the <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Power;</hi> The <hi>Head</hi> of <hi>Principalities,</hi> and <hi>Powers,</hi> and of <hi>every</hi> man, and of the <hi>Church, which is his Body, the fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all, which is in God, the Pillar and ground of Truth, Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Power of God;</hi> And the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> The <hi>way of Life,</hi> the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Life;</hi> The <hi>one</hi> Law-giver, <hi>who is able to ſave, and to deſtroy; Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> to <hi>whom the Father hath committed all Judgement, the Judge</hi> of <hi>all, the King Eternal, Immortal, Inviſible,</hi> the <hi>only wiſe God;</hi> The <hi>bleſſed</hi> and <hi>only</hi> Potentate, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>lords,</hi> who <hi>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath Immortality, dwelling in the Light which no man can approach unto,</hi> whom <hi>no man hath ſeen, nor can ſee, to whom be Honour, and Power Everlaſting,</hi> Amen. Who is <hi>able to ſave to the uttermoſt, them that come to God by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, there is <hi>that</hi> in <hi>every</hi> one of <hi>you, which never conſents to ſin,</hi> nor <hi>was</hi> nor <hi>can</hi> be overcome by <hi>it, which</hi> the <hi>gates of Hell</hi> can <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29826:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> prevail againſt, elſe <hi>it</hi> ſhould <hi>never</hi> ſpeak, <hi>it</hi> ſhould <hi>never</hi> move againſt <hi>that which</hi> is <hi>evil, which</hi> gives the <hi>Law,</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> to <hi>ſin,</hi> reproves, checks, Judges and condemns <hi>it,</hi> be <hi>it never ſo</hi> high, and flowing over, and <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>Kingdom of God;</hi> And <hi>this</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God <hi>is within you, it comes not by obſervation,</hi> ſaid <hi>Chriſt</hi> even to the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> whom <hi>he</hi> called <hi>Serpents,</hi> there was <hi>that</hi> even in <hi>them, which never</hi> was <hi>ſo</hi> overcome by <hi>ſin,</hi> as to <hi>conſent</hi> to <hi>ſin,</hi> but <hi>reproved it,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> was the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>them;</hi> And <hi>this</hi> Nebuchadnezar came to acknowledge, after that <hi>he was driven out from among men; And had eaten graſſe with the Oxen, and his body had been wet with the dew of Heaven, till his hair was grown like Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles feathers, and his nailes like Birds claws, and ſeven times had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over him,</hi> [Sc.] <hi>That the moſt High ruleth in the Kingdoms of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, there is <hi>that</hi> in <hi>every</hi> one of <hi>you</hi> that <hi>limits,</hi> that <hi>ſtops,</hi> that <hi>ſets</hi> the <hi>bounds</hi> to the <hi>rovings</hi> of <hi>your</hi> mindes, and the <hi>out-goings</hi> of <hi>your</hi> thoughts, to the <hi>ends</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> and to the <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> that <hi>it</hi> paſſe not <hi>all</hi> bounds, and that <hi>brings</hi> to <hi>conſideration,</hi> to <hi>coolneſſe,</hi> to a <hi>conſiſtencie</hi> of <hi>things</hi> in <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and to minde <hi>God</hi> in <hi>whom ye live, move, and have your being,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> is <hi>truth, God that made the World, and all things therein, ſeeing that he is Lord of Heaven and Earth, dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, neither is worſhipped with mens hands, as though he needed any thing, ſeeing that he giveth unto all Life, and Breath, and all things, and hath made of one Blood, all Nations of men, for to dwell on all the face of the Earth, and hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their habitation, that they ſhould ſeek the Lord, if happilie they might feel after him, though he be not far from any of us, for in him we live, move, and have our being, for we are his off-ſpring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, there's <hi>that</hi> in <hi>every</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one of <hi>you, which</hi> ſeeks to <hi>gather you</hi> from <hi>your</hi> vaine and wilde immaginations of <hi>God, Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>holy men</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> The <hi>Scriptures,</hi> The <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to the <hi>beginning,</hi> to the <hi>Light, the beginning of the Creation of God, which</hi> ſhewes <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>man</hi> in the <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> wherein <hi>his fooliſh heart is darkened,</hi> and <hi>his minde alienated from the Life of God, through the ignorance that is in him, becauſe of the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his heart,</hi> in that State, the <hi>ſame</hi> is <hi>it,</hi> in <hi>which</hi> only <hi>ye</hi> can know <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit;</hi> And the <hi>Holy men</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> for, <hi>the natural
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29826:4"/> man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſſe unto him, neither can he know them, becauſe they are Spiritually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned;</hi> And, <hi>Where is the wiſe man? Where is the Scribe? Where is the diſputer of this World? Hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdom of this World?</hi> For, <hi>in the wiſdom of God it is, that the World by wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom knows not God, which he is come to confound, even the wiſdom of the wiſe, and to bring to nought the underſtanding of the Prudent; Whom none of the Princes of this World knew, for if they knew it, they would not have crucified the Lord of Glory.</hi> And <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>you</hi> all, the <hi>meaſure</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> which <hi>every</hi> one of <hi>you</hi> have <hi>received wherein to know God,</hi> and, <hi>wherewithal to profit;</hi> Of <hi>which he</hi> will <hi>require an account, which</hi> is as a <hi>grain</hi> of <hi>muſtard</hi> ſeed, unto <hi>which ye</hi> all muſt come, and be guided by, and grow up into <hi>it,</hi> if <hi>ever ye</hi> know the <hi>Lord;</hi> or, the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>his Kingdom,</hi> which conſiſts in <hi>Righteouſneſſe, and Peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> or ſee <hi>his</hi> face, or, be <hi>made</hi> partaker of the <hi>Inheritance</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> in <hi>Light.</hi> And <hi>this</hi> unto <hi>you</hi> all is <hi>is the word of the Lord,</hi> for, <hi>he,</hi> that came to give the <hi>knowledge of Salvation unto his people,</hi> by, <hi>the Remiſſion of their ſins, through the tender mercies of God, whereby the day-ſpring from on high hath viſited us;</hi> Came, to give <hi>light to them that ſit in darkneſſe, and in the ſhaddow of Death, and to guide our feet in the way of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto <hi>this,</hi> therefore, the <hi>meaſure</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>you</hi> all, the <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Light which comes</hi> from <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Saviour</hi> of the <hi>Soul, which</hi> witneſſes for <hi>God,</hi> and againſt <hi>all</hi> evil <hi>which</hi> it ſhews, yea, the <hi>very appearance</hi> of <hi>it,</hi> and reproves, judges and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns <hi>it,</hi> (the <hi>ſame</hi> is <hi>it which</hi> ſhews <hi>you,</hi> what <hi>ye</hi> ſhould do) <hi>which</hi> is <hi>in you,</hi> and <hi>ye</hi> know that <hi>it</hi> is ſo, <hi>which</hi> leads <hi>out</hi> of <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,</hi> to <hi>that which</hi> was <hi>before tranſgreſſion,</hi> the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Salvation;</hi> Apply <hi>your</hi> mindes whilſt <hi>ye</hi> have time, a <hi>little</hi> time, heed <hi>it,</hi> believe in <hi>it,</hi> and obey <hi>it,</hi> whilſt the <hi>door</hi> is <hi>yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen,</hi> whilſt the <hi>Lord</hi> calls on <hi>you,</hi> And <hi>his</hi> Spirit <hi>ſtrives with you;</hi> Whoſe <hi>Spirit</hi> will not <hi>alwayes ſtrive with man,</hi> whilſt <hi>his</hi> Armes are <hi>ſtretched</hi> out to <hi>gather you;</hi> That ſo <hi>ye</hi> may come to know the <hi>things that do belong to your Eternal Peace,</hi> and that <hi>it</hi> may be <hi>well</hi> with <hi>you,</hi> as to that in <hi>every</hi> one of <hi>you,</hi> which muſt <hi>abide for ever.</hi> For, verily, <hi>Friends,</hi> the <hi>time</hi> is <hi>ſhort,</hi> yea, <hi>very ſhort,</hi> and the <hi>Lord is at hand,</hi> and <hi>he</hi> is drawing <hi>near to judgment, he</hi> hath <hi>long</hi> waited <hi>to be Gracious, he</hi> hath born <hi>long,</hi> and ſuffered: <hi>His</hi> Soul
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29826:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> hath <hi>long</hi> been <hi>preſſed</hi> under <hi>you, as a cart is preſſed with ſheaves, he</hi> is <hi>even weary with forbearing;</hi> Yet, loath <hi>he</hi> is that any of <hi>you</hi> ſhould <hi>dy,</hi> but <hi>rather that you ſhould return, and live.</hi> And for <hi>this</hi> purpoſe hath <hi>he</hi> (now) viſited <hi>you,</hi> with <hi>his tender</hi> compaſſion, Therefore, <hi>hear, that your Souls may live;</hi> For, <hi>this I</hi> teſtifie to <hi>you</hi> in the <hi>name</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and as being <hi>moved</hi> of <hi>him, whoſe</hi> word <hi>it</hi> is, that to <hi>thoſe</hi> of <hi>you,</hi> unto whom <hi>his tender</hi> viſitations have come, and are <hi>ſtill</hi> rejected, <hi>after this your hour, there is no more, but ye will Eternally be concluded, with the God, whom ye ſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, now, leaſt what <hi>I</hi> have aſſerted concerning the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>you, which witneſſeth</hi> for <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Chriſt which</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves, and, <hi>makes</hi> manifeſt the <hi>way</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Saviour</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> and there is <hi>no</hi> other; Should ſeem ſtrange unto <hi>you,</hi> or <hi>I</hi> to be a <hi>ſetter forth of a ſtrange God,</hi> of a <hi>Principle,</hi> or <hi>Principles, ſtrange</hi> and <hi>forreign</hi> to <hi>your</hi> profeſſions, look, <hi>ye Students</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> into <hi>your</hi> own Books, eſpecially <hi>ſuch</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> as are uſually read for the initiating <hi>you</hi> into the <hi>ground,</hi> or <hi>Principle</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> and ſee whether <hi>they</hi> do not ſpeak what <hi>I</hi> ſay</p>
            <p>For <hi>example,</hi> look into Chriſtopher de Sancto Germano (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Seyn German) his</hi> Dialogue concerning the <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Laws of England,</hi> &amp;c. And ſee, whether <hi>he</hi> doth not tell <hi>you</hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>thing</hi> in <hi>man,</hi> as is called <hi>Syntereſis,</hi> unto <hi>which he</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects as the <hi>ground</hi> and <hi>bottom</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> And of <hi>which</hi> (Chap. 11.) in anſwer to <hi>this</hi> queſtion placed in the <hi>head</hi> of it. (Sc.) Quid ſit ſintereſis? (<hi>what is Syntereſis?</hi> He <hi>thus</hi> ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>Sintereſis eſt vis motiva, ſeu potentia naturalis, animae rationalis, quae ſemper eſt nata figi, in ſuperioribus partibus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimae, movens, &amp; Stimulans ad bonum, &amp; abhorrens malum, &amp; ideo ſecundam ſintereſim, non eſt errare, neque peccare, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut nec circa principium in ſpeculabilibus (that is) <hi>Sintereſis is the living virtue, or power natural of the reaſonable Soul, which is born al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to reſide in the ſuperiour parts of the Soul, moving and pricking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; And abhorring evil, and therefore according to Syntereſis, there is neither ſinning nor erring as there is not about the principle in things that are under ſpeculation.</hi> Now, <hi>what</hi> is <hi>that which ſinneth not,</hi> but <hi>the born of God?</hi> And <hi>what</hi> is <hi>that</hi> according unto <hi>which</hi> one <hi>cannot ſin, or erre,</hi> but, <hi>the ſeed, which remaines in him that he cannot ſin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is born of God?</hi> And <hi>what</hi> is <hi>that which moves and pricks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to good, and abhorrs evil,</hi> but, the <hi>principle of God which is</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore placed in <hi>man,</hi> to bring <hi>him</hi> unto <hi>God?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:29826:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Again</hi> Hanc quoque Syntereſim, ideò poſuit Deus in homine, ut ſervetur ordo &amp; connexio rerum; <hi>This Syntereſis God therefore hath put into man, that the Order and Connexion of things might be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> Now <hi>what</hi> is <hi>that which</hi> preſerveth the <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Connexion</hi> of things, but <hi>that which</hi> upholdeth <hi>all</hi> things by the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Power? And <hi>what</hi> is <hi>that which</hi> upholdeth <hi>all</hi> things by the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Power, but <hi>that</hi> by <hi>which the worlds were made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreover,</hi> Quae ſyntereſis non poteſt totalitèr extingui, nec eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am in damnatis; Sed tamen quantum ad actum poteſt ad tempus impedire, five propter tenebram obcaecationis, ſive propter laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viam delectationis, ſive propter duritiem obſtinationis; Propter tenebram obcaecationis impeditur ſyntereſis, ne malo remurmuret, pro eo quod malum creditur eſſe bonum, ſicut in haereticis, qui morientes pro impietate erroris, credunt ſe mori pro pietate fidei; Propter laſciviam delectationis, quando, Scilicet, ſyntereſis ita abſorbetur, ut remorſus non habet locum, quia carnales homines tanto impetu delectationis feruntur, ut ratio non habet locum propter duritiem obſtinationis impeditur etiam ſintereſis, ne ad bonum ſtimulet, ſicut in damnatis qui adeo ſunt in malo obſtinati ut nunquam poſſunt ad bonum inclinare, propterea quantum ad illum actum, quo ſyntereſis ſtimulat ad bonum, poteſt in illis dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis dici extincta, non tamen extincta ſimplicitèr, quia habet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium uſum, ſcilicet remurmurationem contra malum paenae quae maximè vigebit in damnatis, unde ſyntereſis murmurabit in dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis contra culpam in relatione tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad poenam. Et ſic ſyntereſis quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adalique<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> actu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> impedire poteſt nunquàm, tamen extincta po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt univerſalitèr quantum ad omne actum, &amp; quantum ad omne tempus. (That is) <hi>Which Syntereſis cannot totally be extinguiſhed no not in the damned; But nevertheleſs, as to act, and time, it may be ſaid to be hindred, either, by reaſon of the darkneſs of blindneſs, or the wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of delight, or the hardneſſe of obstinacy, by reaſon of the darkneſs of blindneſs Syntereſis may be hindred, that it remurmurates not for that evil which it believes to be good; As in Hereticks, who dying for the impiety of error, do believe that they die for the piety of Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by reaſon of the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs of delight, when as Syntereſis is ſo abſorbed that remorſe hath no place, becauſe carnal men are ſo hurried with the violence of delight, that reaſon hath no place, by reaſon of the hardneſs of obſtinacy;</hi> Synte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſis <hi>is alſo hindred, that it pricks not unto good, as it is in the damned, who are ſo hardned in evil, that they can never incline to good, for which cauſe, in reference to that act, by which Syntereſis pricks unto good, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be ſaid in the damned to be extinguiſhed, not ſimply extinguiſhed, becauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29826:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> it hath another uſe, to wit, the remurmuration againſt the evil of pain, which greatly lives in the damned, from whence Syntereſis will murmur in the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt the fault in relation onely to the pain; And ſo Syntereſis in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to ſome Act may be ſaid to be hindred but it can never be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally extinguiſhed, in reference to every Act, and as to all time.</hi>—And <hi>what</hi> is <hi>this</hi> but the <hi>witneſſe</hi> of <hi>God, which</hi> can <hi>never</hi> be <hi>raſed</hi> out, though by reaſon of the <hi>blindeneſſe</hi> of <hi>mens</hi> minds, and the <hi>hardneſſe of their</hi> hearts, and <hi>their living in pleaſures, it</hi> anſwers not; <hi>The Worm that never dies and the fire that never goes out?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Furthermore,</hi> Syntereſis etiam eſt principium, quoad ſpeculativa eſt quoad operativa, exemplum de ſpeculativis, ut omne totum eſt majus ſua parte, quodlibet eſt, vel non eſt. Exemplum de ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rativis, ut nullum malum eſt faciendum, bonum eſt proſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, &amp; ſimilia, &amp; id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Syntereſis dicitur a quibuſdam lex ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, quia principia legis rationis miniſtrat, quae ei inſunt a natura. (That is) <hi>Syntereſis is alſo a principle as to things that appertain to ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation and operation. Example of things that appertain to Speculation, as every whole is greater than its part, every thing is or not is example of things that appertain to operation, as no evil is to be done, good is to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and ſuch like; And therefore Syntereſis is called by ſome the Law of Reaſon, becauſe it Miniſters the Principles of the Law of Reaſon, which are in it by Nature.</hi> And <hi>what</hi> is the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>Seeing</hi> and <hi>Doing, which</hi> comprehends <hi>all things,</hi> but <hi>that</hi> by <hi>which all things were made,</hi> which <hi>Principle</hi> muſt be <hi>in man,</hi> or there can be <hi>no</hi> ſuch thing in <hi>man as Seeing</hi> and <hi>Doing.</hi> For a <hi>thing</hi> is not, nor can be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>its</hi> Principle; And <hi>what</hi> is <hi>that which Miniſters</hi> the <hi>Principles</hi> to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Reaſon, which are in it by Nature,</hi> but <hi>that</hi> which is the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> viz. the <hi>head of every man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly.</hi> Syntereſis quoque a quibuſdam ſic deſcribitur, Syntere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis eſt potentia nata aſſentire naturaliter principio practico evidenti ex terminis dictanti, id eſt ſignificanti in Univerſali, aliquid ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum vel fugiendum, &amp; per hoc quod dicitur potentia, excludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur actus &amp; habitus acquiſitus, &amp; dicitur nata aſſentire, quia non oporter quod actu aſſentiat, quia etiam potentia dicitur Syntereſis, dum actu nullum principium apprehendit, &amp; dicitur naturaliter aſſentire, id eſt, ſtatim apprehenſis terminis aſſentire, quia non requirit probationem, vel diſcurſum ad hoc quod aſſentiat, ſed ex conditione ſuae naturae, ſtatim apprehenſis terminis non poteſt non aſſentire, dicitur etiam (evidenti ex terminis) quia reſpectu principii eviden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>per experientiam: Non dicitur Syntereſis eo,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29826:6"/> quod tale Principium apprehenſum poteſt ignorari, &amp; etiam addit (in univerſali) ad excludendum Conſcientiam, quae eſt judicium concluſionis practicae in particulari diſtantis. That is, <hi>Syntereſis</hi> alſo, <hi>by ſome is thus diſcribed, Syntereſis is a Power born to aſſent natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to a practical principle, evident by the tearms dictating, that is, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying in every thing, ſomething to be done, or ſomething to be avoided; And by this that it is ſaid</hi>—a Power—<hi>Acquired Act and Habit is excluded; And it is ſaid</hi>—Born to aſcent—<hi>Becauſe it need not that it aſcent by the Act, in regard that Syntereſis is even called a Power, whileſt it apprehends no principle by the Act, and it is ſaid</hi>—naturally to aſcent—<hi>That is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, the tearms being apprehended, to aſcent, becauſe it doth not require proof or diſcuſſion unto that, to which it aſcents, but out of the condition of its own nature, preſently the terms being apprehended, it cannot but aſſent. It is alſo ſaid</hi>—evident by the Terms—<hi>becauſe in reſpect of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple evident by experience, Syntereſis is not ſaid, in it, that ſuch a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple being apprehended, it can be ignorant; And it is added</hi>—in every thing—<hi>For the excluding of Conſcience, which is the Judgement of a Practical concluſion, dictating in the particular.</hi> And <hi>what</hi> is <hi>this,</hi> but <hi>that which ſeeth all things,</hi> not as <hi>man, but as they are,</hi> and is <hi>greater than Conſcience?</hi> Thus far <hi>Seyngerman</hi> in anſwer to the <hi>queſtion</hi> Quid ſit Syntereſis? <hi>What is Syntereſis?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, for the <hi>derivation</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> do not your Books ſay, that it is derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which, <hi>they ſay,</hi> may be called conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatio a <hi>conſervation</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> conſervo to <hi>conſerve</hi> or <hi>keep together,</hi> Unde ea pars animae (<hi>ſay they</hi>) quae vitiis adverſatur, &amp; ſeſe ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per immaculatum a vitiis cupit conſervare, &amp; perpetrata malo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuò arguit, Syntereſis dicitur; That is, <hi>From whence that part of the ſoul which is againſt evil, and alwayes deſires to keep it ſelf unſpotted of it, and continually argueth againſt evil perpetrated, is called</hi> Syntereſis. And <hi>what</hi> is <hi>that</hi> but the Religion <hi>which is pure</hi> and <hi>undefiled before God, and the Father, which</hi> keepeth <hi>it</hi> ſelf <hi>unſpotted of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much of <hi>Syntereſis</hi> which <hi>ye</hi> lay as the <hi>ground</hi> or <hi>Principle</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>derivation</hi> of <hi>it,</hi> and what <hi>it</hi> is and ſignifies.</p>
            <p>Now as to <hi>LAW.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for this look again into <hi>your</hi> Books, and ſee whether <hi>they</hi> ſpeak not of <hi>LAW,</hi> as <hi>they</hi> have of <hi>Syntereſis,</hi> and <hi>both</hi> the <hi>ſame</hi> as <hi>I</hi> have aſſerted?</p>
            <p>For Example.<note place="margin">See Bracto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> Lib. 1 Chap <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Lex eſt (<hi>ſay they</hi>) ſanctio ſancta jubens honeſta, prohibens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria—<hi>Law is a holy ſanction Commanding things honeſt, forbidding the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29826:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> contrary.</hi>—And, what is <hi>this</hi> but the <hi>holy Commandement?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>hs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus of <hi>LAW</hi> in <hi>its General</hi> difinition.</p>
            <p>More <hi>particularly</hi> of <hi>LAW,</hi> as <hi>ye</hi> diſtinguiſh <hi>it</hi> into the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> * your <hi>two great</hi> foundations of <hi>Law,</hi> which <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Reaſon ye</hi> call <hi>thoſe two great lights which God hath ſet in the firmament of</hi> your <hi>heart.</hi> And, as to the term <hi>LAW.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>Nature.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>ch</hi> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ok—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>W</hi>—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>g 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seyngerman</hi> ſaith (and generally <hi>your</hi> Law Books) lex Naturae eſt lex Eterna.—<hi>The law of Nature, is the law Eternal.</hi>—And who is the <hi>law Eternal,</hi> but the <hi>King Immortal?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Phyloſophers</hi> (ye ſay) call it -Juſtitia Originalis- <hi>Original Juſtice,</hi>—now <hi>who</hi> is <hi>Original Juſtice,</hi> but <hi>He</hi> by whom <hi>Kings reign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>ch</hi> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ok <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>W,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>g. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and Princes decree Juſtice? * Finch</hi> in <hi>his</hi> Book intituled-<hi>LAW</hi>—thus diſcribes <hi>it</hi>—lex Naturae eſt ratio ſumma inſita in hominis Natura, quae jubet ea quae faciendaſunt, prohibetque contraria—(that is) <hi>The law of Nature, is that Sovereign Reaſon fixed in mans Nature, which commandeth thoſe things which are to be done, and forbideth the contrary.</hi>—And <hi>what</hi> is <hi>this,</hi> but the <hi>ſame</hi> with the <hi>general</hi> defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>LAW</hi> as aforeſaid?</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>g.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finch</hi> ſaith again, <hi>Chap. 2. pa.</hi> 4. in the words of <hi>Tully</hi> which he quotes under that head—Lex eſt radius divini luminis, and, recta ratio ſummi Jovis—(that is) <hi>Law is a beam of Divine Light,</hi> and <hi>right Reaſon of the Sover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gn God.</hi>—Now, <hi>who</hi> is the <hi>Divine light,</hi> but <hi>Chriſt the Light of the World?</hi> And <hi>what</hi> is the <hi>Beam</hi> of <hi>Divine light,</hi> but the <hi>light of Chriſt, that lighteth every man that cometh into the World?</hi> And <hi>what</hi> is the <hi>Beam of the Sovereign God,</hi> but the <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of God?</hi> For the <hi>Beam</hi> is of the <hi>ſame</hi> Nature with the <hi>Light,</hi> and comes from <hi>it</hi> and from the <hi>Light</hi> cannot be ſeparated.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, as to the Term, or word <hi>LAW.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finch</hi> tells <hi>ye Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, page</hi> 2. of <hi>his</hi> Book aforeſaid, that the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (Thorah) <hi>from the Root,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rah) <hi>which is to Teach becauſe it is the Doctrine of Truth,</hi> as (ſaith he) <hi>Plato ſaith in in his</hi> 9th. <hi>Book,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Leges ad hominum Doctrinam ponun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,—<hi>Laws are for the teaching of men.—So that</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>LAW car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes with it, and hath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as it were incloſed in the Name and Nature of it, thoſe three Laws. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and Golden Chain of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all good learning,</hi> Lex veritatis, Lex Juſtitiae, Lex Sapientiae—<hi>the Law of Truth, the Law of Juſtice, the Law of Wiſdom; And therefore is not onely</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Scientia, <hi>Science,</hi> (which word the Phyloſophers uſe whereby to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29826:7"/> expreſſe the Divine underſtanding) <hi>but</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Scientificiſſima, <hi>Scientificiſſimous</hi> (or the ſuperlative efficient of an underſtanding Divine) <hi>Whereupon</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Plato telleth us,</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Plato Lib. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rep: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Nomen menti con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentaneum poſſidet Divina nobis &amp; admirabillia Lex—Law, a Name conſentaneous, (or agreeable) to the minde (<hi>that is to God</hi> faith Finch) <hi>whom the Philoſophers call</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Mens, <hi>the Minde, which is Truth, Wiſdom, and Juſtice it ſelf</hi>) poſſeſſeth in us Divine, and things moſt admirable, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſo that the Name it ſelf (ſaith he) doth ſhew the Author from whence it came; And, as he ſaith</hi> (that is Plato) Qui tanti talem genuere parentes? How great are thoſe parents which have brought forth ſuch a Child?—Now, <hi>who</hi> is <hi>he</hi> that <hi>carries with him, and hath (as it were) incloſed in his Name, and nature thoſe three Lawes, and Golden Chain of all good learning</hi> (to wit) <hi>the law of Truth, the law of Juſtice, the law of Wiſdom,</hi> who <hi>therefore is not onely Science, but Scientificiſſimous,</hi> whoſe <hi>Name is agreeable to God, to the minde</hi> from whence <hi>he</hi> came, who <hi>is Truth, Wiſdom, and Juſtice it-ſelf,</hi> and <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth in us Divine,</hi> and <hi>things moſt Admirable,</hi> whoſe <hi>Name ſhews the Author from whence he came,</hi> of whoſe <hi>Father</hi> it may be ſaid, <hi>How great is he that hath begetten ſuch a Son?</hi> But the <hi>Son</hi> to whom the <hi>Father</hi> ſaith, <hi>thy Throne O God, is for Ever and Ever, a Scepter of Righteouſneſſe is the Scepter of thy Kingdom; Thou haſt loved Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and hated Iniquity, therefore God, even thy God hath anointed thee with the Oyl of gladneſſe above thy fellows. And thou Lord in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning haſt laid the foundation of the Earth, and the Heavens are the works of thy Hands, they ſhall periſh but thou remaineſt, and they all ſhall wax old as doth a Garment, and as a Veſture ſhalt thou fold them up, and they ſhall be changed, but thou art the ſame, and thine years ſhall not faile.</hi> The <hi>Son</hi> on whoſe <hi>ſhoulders the Government lies,</hi> the <hi>word of God which abideth for Ever;</hi> The <hi>LAW of the Lord which is perfect, converting the Soul, the Teſtimony of the Lord which is ſure, making wiſe the ſimple, the Statutes of the Lord which are right, rejoycing the Heart;</hi> The <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the Lord which is pure enlightning the eyes:</hi> The <hi>Fear of the Lord which is clean enduring for ever.</hi> The <hi>Judgements of the Lord which are true, and Righteous altogether, more to be deſred than Gold, yea than fine Gold, ſweeter alſo than the Hony or the Hony-comb?</hi> And <hi>who</hi> is the <hi>Doctrine of Truth,</hi> but <hi>he who</hi> is the <hi>Teacher of his People,</hi> in <hi>whoſe mouth was the LAW of Truth, and Iniqvity was not found in his lips?</hi> And, <hi>who</hi> puts <hi>Laws</hi> (as of Right) <hi>for the Teaching of men,</hi> but <hi>he</hi> of whom <hi>Moſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruly ſaid unto the Fathers, A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you of your Brethren like unto me, him ſhall ye hear in all things whatſoever
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29826:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> he ſhall ſay unto You: And it ſhall come to paſs, that every Soul that will not hear that Prophet, ſhall be deſtroyed from among the People,</hi> The <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> ſaith <hi>Finch</hi> in the ſame <hi>Chapter</hi> and <hi>Page;—Laws are Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or Poſitive.</hi> Tully <hi>in his Oration pro Mitone taketh us out this Leſſon.</hi>—Eſt enim haec non ſcripta ſed nata lex, quam non didicimus, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepimus, legimus, verum e natura ipſa arripuimus, hauſimus, expreſſimus; ad quam non docti ſed nati, non inſtituti ſed imbuti ſumus.—<hi>For this LAW is not written but born, which we have not learned, received, read, but out of Nature it ſelf have drawn, ſuck't and expreſſed; unto which we are not taught, but born, not inſtituted, but endued</hi>—In <hi>his firſt Book</hi> de Legibus <hi>he</hi> (that is <hi>Tully) doth again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat it;</hi>—Conſtituendi verò juris ab illa Summa Lege Capiamus. Exordium, quae ſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is omnibus ante nata eſt, quam Scripta lex ulla.—That is, <hi>But let us take the Riſe of conſtituting Law from that Soveraign Law, which is born before all Ages, before any Law was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi>—where <hi>this Native Law he</hi> (that is Tully) <hi>calleth the Soveraign Law, as that from which all other Laws do ſtream.</hi>—And laſtly, ſaith <hi>Finch. Native, are thoſe Laws which are in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s of themſelves, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unchangeable and perpetual.</hi>—Now <hi>what</hi> is <hi>that</hi> LAW, <hi>that is not Written but Born,</hi> which <hi>we have not learned, received, read, unto which we are not taught but born, not inſtituted but endued,</hi> but the <hi>law put into the Mind,</hi> and <hi>writ in the Heart,</hi> not <hi>with Ink and Paper, but the Spirit of the living God,</hi> the <hi>New Covenant, which the Lord ſaid he would make with the houſe of Iſrael, after thoſe dayes,</hi> even that <hi>he</hi> would <hi>put his Laws into their Mind, and write them in their Hearts,</hi> and that <hi>He</hi> would <hi>be unto them a God,</hi> and that <hi>they</hi> ſhould <hi>be to him a People;</hi> and that <hi>they</hi> ſhould <hi>not Teach every Man his Neighbour, and every Man his Brother, ſaying, Know the Lord, for all ſhould know him from the leaſt unto the greateſt, for</hi> that <hi>he</hi> would <hi>be Merciful to their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, and their Iniquities he would remember no more?</hi> And <hi>what</hi> is <hi>that Nature it ſelf out of which we draw, ſuck, and expreſse it,</hi> but the <hi>Nature by which the Gentiles which had not the Law, did the things contained in the Law, theſe having not the Law, were a Law unto themſelves; which ſhewed the work of the Law written in their Hearts, their Conſciences alſo bearing Witneſſe;</hi> The <hi>Nature</hi> (Divine) the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion which is by Nature, which keeps the Righteouſneſſe of the Law; which fulfills the Law,</hi> by <hi>which</hi> is judged <hi>he who by the Letter and Circumciſion tranſgreſſes the Law,</hi> even <hi>hee</hi> who <hi>is called a Jew,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29826:8"/> and reſteth in the Law, and maketh his boaſt of God, and knoweth his Will, and approveth the Things that are more excellent, being inſtructed out of the Law, and is confident that he himſelf is a guide to the blind; a light to them who ſit in darkneſſe; an Inſtructer of the fooliſh; a Teacher of Babes; which hath the form of Knowledge and Truth in the Law; and yet through breaking the Law diſhonors God;</hi> whoſe <hi>Circumciſion is made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion,</hi> but the <hi>uncircumciſion</hi> of the other <hi>is counted for Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion: For, he is not a Jew which is one outwardly, neither is that Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, which is outward in the fleſh; but he is a Jew which is one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and Circumciſion is that of the Heart; in the ſpirit and not in the letter, whoſe praiſe is not of Men but of God;</hi> The <hi>Divine Nature</hi> of <hi>which they are made partakers, who have eſcaped the Corruption that is in the World through luſt?</hi> And <hi>who</hi> is the <hi>Soveraign Law from whom all other Laws do ſtream, which is born before all ages, before any Law was Written;</hi> but <hi>he</hi> who is <hi>without beginning of dayes, or end of life,</hi> who <hi>cannot be written?</hi> And <hi>whoſe Laws are Native, or in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s of themſelves, and therefore <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeable, and Perpetual,</hi> but <hi>his</hi> who <hi>changeth not, in whom is no variableneſſe, or ſhadow of changing,</hi> who is <hi>a Prieſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever after the order of</hi> Melchiſedeck, <hi>whoſe Laws</hi> are <hi>like him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, <hi>indeed,</hi> were not ſome <hi>ſuch</hi> thing as <hi>this</hi> laid for the <hi>ground,</hi> what <hi>true</hi> pretence, or <hi>colour</hi> of Reaſon is there for the <hi>Common</hi> (or <hi>any) Law</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> ſeeing, that the <hi>Breaſt</hi> of the <hi>Judge,</hi> or that <hi>within him,</hi> from whence <hi>he</hi> Judgeth, is the <hi>principle</hi> thereof, which if it be <hi>corrupt, unreaſonable</hi> and <hi>evil, ſuch</hi> muſt needs be the <hi>judgement</hi> which proceedeth from <hi>it,</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> is the <hi>judgement</hi> which proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not from the <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> And were there not <hi>ſuch</hi> a thing in <hi>man,</hi> as the <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> what <hi>Right</hi> have <hi>any</hi> to <hi>Rule,</hi> or to <hi>what</hi> end are <hi>Laws,</hi> of <hi>Right,</hi> among <hi>men?</hi> ſeeing, that the <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>God</hi> it is <hi>only</hi> that makes <hi>man</hi> to differ from the <hi>beaſt that periſheth;</hi> and aſſoon (yea ſooner, (if <hi>I</hi> may ſo ſay) becauſe the <hi>beaſt</hi> hath not that underſtanding, for the <hi>Devil</hi> to work in as <hi>unreaſonable</hi> man) may the <hi>Beaſt</hi> be taught to <hi>ceaſe to do evil,</hi> and <hi>to learn to do well,</hi> as <hi>man</hi> in <hi>this</hi> ſtate: For, <hi>the Ox knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters crib, but Iſrael doth not know, my People doth not conſider.</hi> And, <hi>man bein in honour abideth not, he is like the beaſt that periſh.</hi> And <hi>wiſe Agur</hi> ſaid of <hi>himſelf, ſurely I am more bruitiſh than any man, and have not the underſtanding of a man, I neither learned wiſdom, nor have the knowledge of the Holy.</hi> But <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Principle</hi> as <hi>this</hi> being in <hi>man,</hi> is the <hi>ground</hi> or <hi>reaſon</hi> (though it be <hi>little</hi> known) why there is <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſſe</hi> of <hi>right</hi> in the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> and <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſſe</hi> of <hi>Obedience</hi> unto <hi>them,</hi> even as <hi>thoſe</hi> who govern, or, are <hi>under</hi> them, have <hi>more</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:29826:9"/> or <hi>leſſe</hi> of <hi>this,</hi> or as <hi>this</hi> works <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſſe,</hi> or <hi>is</hi> in the <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>them.</hi> And the <hi>being</hi> of <hi>this</hi> in <hi>man</hi> is the <hi>reaſon,</hi> why <hi>Nations</hi> are not <hi>utterly</hi> deſtroyed, and mankinde <hi>raſed</hi> out from <hi>off the face of the Earth,</hi> which the <hi>Devil</hi> would ſoon do, could he <hi>this</hi> get over, and <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> though man attributes it too much to <hi>his</hi> wiſdom and ſtrength, and gives not the <hi>Glory</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> nor ſees <hi>his</hi> working; And the <hi>want</hi> of the <hi>knowing</hi> and <hi>working</hi> of <hi>this</hi> in <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> is the <hi>reaſon</hi> of <hi>moſt</hi> of the <hi>wars</hi> and <hi>deſolations in the Earth,</hi> but <hi>this</hi> coming to be <hi>known,</hi> and to <hi>work,</hi> the <hi>occaſions</hi> of <hi>wars</hi> which <hi>make deſolate,</hi> will <hi>ceaſe,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> oppreſſion, and <hi>that</hi> which preſerves the <hi>Creation,</hi> by <hi>which it was made, which</hi> is <hi>tender</hi> to <hi>that which it hath made,</hi> and redeems <hi>it</hi> from the <hi>vanity</hi> unto which <hi>it</hi> was <hi>made</hi> ſubject, will <hi>guide</hi> and <hi>rule;</hi> And ſo <hi>all</hi> things will be brought into <hi>their right</hi> courſe and order again as <hi>before</hi> the <hi>fall,</hi> which <hi>turned all</hi> things <hi>out</hi> of <hi>Order,</hi> and <hi>inverted</hi> the <hi>right</hi> courſe and order of <hi>things</hi> in <hi>which</hi> ſtate things ſtand, till <hi>that</hi> which was <hi>before</hi> the <hi>Fall,</hi> from <hi>which man</hi> was driven in the <hi>Fall,</hi> doth <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>guide.</hi> And for the manifeſtation of <hi>this</hi> the <hi>Creature</hi> groaneth, and travelleth in <hi>pain together till now,</hi> even for the manifeſtation of the <hi>ſons</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that <hi>it</hi> may not be <hi>made</hi> ſubject unto <hi>vanity;</hi> For, <hi>the earneſt expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Creature waiteth for the manifeſtation of the ſons of God, for the Creature was made ſubject unto vanity, not willingly, but by reaſon of him who hath ſubjected the ſame in hope, becauſe that the Creature it ſelfe alſo ſhall be delivered from the bondage of corruption, into the glorious liberty of the Children of God. For we know that the whole Creation groaneth, and travelleth in pain together until now, and not only they but our ſelves alſo, which have the firſt fruits of the ſpirit, even we our ſelves groan within our ſelves, waiting for the Adoption, to wit, the Redemption of our Bodie.</hi> And <hi>this</hi> viz. <hi>the bringing</hi> of <hi>man</hi> back to the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>him,</hi> to <hi>lead</hi> and <hi>guide him,</hi> from <hi>which he</hi> is gone, is the <hi>work which</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> is <hi>now</hi> doing <hi>in the Earth,</hi> and unto <hi>which he</hi> hath brought <hi>thouſands</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in <hi>theſe</hi> Nations, and <hi>which he will not ſlack his hand till he hath finiſhed. The Lord hath ſpoken it,</hi> Glory to <hi>Him</hi> for ever, <hi>who is cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>day to dawn,</hi> and <hi>the ſhadows to fly away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, were it ſo, that <hi>man</hi> knew and believed in, and obeyed the <hi>Principle</hi> of God in <hi>him,</hi> and grew up <hi>therein,</hi> and from <hi>it</hi> gave <hi>judgement</hi> (which <hi>by reaſon of the darkneſs, and ignorance that is in him,</hi> he <hi>little</hi> underſtands, and believes <hi>leſſe;</hi> And, therefore, is <hi>oft</hi> times putting <hi>darkneſſe for light,</hi> and <hi>light for darkneſſe, bitter things for ſweet</hi> and <hi>ſweet for bitter,</hi> as he is ſwayed by <hi>paſſion</hi> and <hi>private</hi> intereſt, not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29826:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> knowing the Lord, nor his Principle in <hi>him.</hi>) The <hi>Common</hi> Law would be <hi>moſt</hi> excellent, and the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> thereof <hi>exceeding</hi> uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and <hi>most</hi> ſuitable to <hi>this</hi> People, the benefit of <hi>which,</hi> as it is, they would <hi>more</hi> feel, were the <hi>Spirit</hi> that Adminiſters <hi>it,</hi> as ſimple, and <hi>plain,</hi> as were the hearts of <hi>them</hi> who gave the <hi>Preſidents.</hi> For, as <hi>profeſſion</hi> without the <hi>life</hi> hath abounded, ſo hath <hi>deceit,</hi> which is the reaſon, why the <hi>preſent</hi> age is <hi>more</hi> oppreſſive, and perplexing in the <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>more</hi> dilatory, and wrong in the <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of <hi>them</hi> than were the <hi>ages</hi> in the <hi>deepeſt</hi> time of <hi>darkest</hi> Popery, who had <hi>leſs</hi> profeſſion, but more ſimplicity as the <hi>things</hi> themſelves <hi>make</hi> manifeſt. However, the <hi>principle</hi> of it ſo far, as in the <hi>Notion,</hi> it is grounded upon, and <hi>refers</hi> to, and <hi>is</hi> the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>God</hi> (as I have ſhewed out of <hi>your</hi> own Books that ſo <hi>it is</hi>) is <hi>good</hi> and <hi>right,</hi> and <hi>no</hi> other than <hi>that</hi> of <hi>which</hi> I have ſpoken, and unto <hi>which I</hi> have directed <hi>you,</hi> as the <hi>way</hi> to <hi>God.</hi> And the <hi>Lord</hi> hath promiſed that <hi>he</hi> will <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Judges, as at the firſt, and Counſellors, as in the beginning, who</hi> were <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>knew,</hi> and were <hi>guided</hi> by, and <hi>judged</hi> from the <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of God in <hi>them;</hi> Which doth <hi>none iniquity,</hi> nor can <hi>evil touch it;</hi> Which <hi>renders to every one his due,</hi> and <hi>judges for God:</hi> as did <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> whom all <hi>Iſrael</hi> followed; The <hi>Judgement which</hi> proceedeth from <hi>that</hi> pure Principle, being <hi>that</hi> which onely reacheth to the <hi>ſame</hi> in <hi>every</hi> man, and <hi>ſubjecteth</hi> unto <hi>it,</hi> from <hi>which</hi> when there was <hi>none</hi> that judged, it was ſo that there was <hi>no King in Iſrael;</hi> And when the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> went from the <hi>Judges</hi> who <hi>judged</hi> from <hi>it,</hi> and ſaid to <hi>Samuel, give us a King to judge us,</hi> and <hi>nay but we will have a King over us, that we alſo may be like all the Nations.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> ſaid to <hi>Samuel, they have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me, that I ſhould not reign over them.</hi> And the <hi>time is at hand wherein this promiſe ſhall be fulfilled,</hi> after the <hi>hour is over which is coming, which will not hold very long, though it will be very ſharp, but ſhall end in this, even in Reign of the Seed of God over all for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Look <hi>ye</hi> Profeſſors of Divinity into the <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> and ſee what <hi>they</hi> ſay, as to the <hi>Queſtion</hi> (Sc.) <hi>where muſt a man begin?</hi> There are <hi>many</hi> rovings in <hi>mans</hi> minde, <hi>many</hi> immaginations driv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>up</hi> and <hi>down, this</hi> way, and <hi>that</hi> way, where muſt a <hi>man</hi> ſtop? Where muſt <hi>he</hi> begin? For he that <hi>never</hi> begins, can <hi>never</hi> come to the <hi>end</hi> that's certain; And <hi>he</hi> that goes wrong, the <hi>longer he</hi> ſo goes and the <hi>faster,</hi> the <hi>further he</hi> is from <hi>his</hi> journeys end, and the <hi>more is his</hi> ſorrow. So that a <hi>beginning</hi> a <hi>man</hi> muſt have, and to that <hi>he</hi> muſt come, and it muſt be in the <hi>Truth</hi> too, or it will not be well
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29826:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> with <hi>him,</hi> and there <hi>he</hi> muſt begin, and there <hi>he</hi> muſt ſtop. But <hi>where must he begin?</hi> At <hi>what muſt he ſtop? [Friends,</hi> theſe things are fundamental] do <hi>they</hi> not ſay, that when ye come to Objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quo ſiſtendum eſt, <hi>when ye are come to the Principle of Seeing, and knowing, ye muſt stop there,</hi> or, there <hi>ye</hi> muſt <hi>begin</hi> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ye</hi> have found out <hi>that,</hi> when <hi>ye</hi> are come to <hi>that?</hi> And is, or can <hi>this</hi> be any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the <hi>Light of Christ?</hi> The <hi>beginning of the Creation of God;</hi> the <hi>meaſure</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> the <hi>Divine</hi> Principle, the <hi>Eternal</hi> Eye in <hi>man,</hi> which <hi>onely</hi> can <hi>perceive the Things of God, for they are Spiritually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned,</hi> which <hi>leads</hi> to <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Saviour</hi> of the <hi>Soul, who</hi> is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the <hi>Beginning</hi> and the <hi>End</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> and the <hi>Last, who is,</hi> and <hi>who was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>who is to come, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord God Almighty, which</hi> is the <hi>Door,</hi> and adminiſters <hi>the entrance into the Kingdom of God; which</hi> is the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>ſeeing</hi> and <hi>knowing</hi> the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God?</hi> And the <hi>reaſon</hi> is <hi>plain.</hi> For, till a <hi>man</hi> comes to <hi>this,</hi> he is <hi>loſt</hi> and <hi>blind,</hi> and <hi>cannot ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>far off,</hi> nor <hi>underſtand the things that appertain to his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Peace,</hi> the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>things that are of the Divine nature.</hi> And <hi>this</hi> Spiritual man <hi>judgeth all things,</hi> but <hi>he himſelf is judged of no man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> Look <hi>ye</hi> Readers of Phyloſophy, into the <hi>Ethicks,</hi> and tell <hi>me</hi> whether <hi>their</hi> anſwer to this <hi>great</hi> Queſtion, (Sc.) <hi>What is Truth?</hi> Be not <hi>this,</hi> viz. Quod ſiſtit intellectum veritas eſt (that is) <hi>that which ſtayes</hi> (ſtops, limmits, bounds) <hi>the understanding</hi> (or mind of man) <hi>is Truth,</hi> which <hi>Principle Paul</hi> ſpake to in the <hi>Phyloſophers</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> when <hi>he</hi> ſaid, that <hi>God</hi> had <hi>made of one blood all Nations of men, to dwell on all the face of the earth,</hi> and had <hi>determined the times before appointed and the bounds of their habitation that they ſhould ſeek the Lord, if happily they might feel after him, and find him, though he be not far from every one of us, for in him we live, move, and have our being,</hi> &amp;c. of <hi>which I have</hi> ſpoken. And the <hi>reaſon</hi> of <hi>this is</hi> manifeſt, for <hi>man</hi> being <hi>dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> from <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>fall, loſt</hi> and <hi>wandering up and down on the face of the Earth,</hi> that <hi>which</hi> brings <hi>him</hi> back again, which puts <hi>him</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</hi> which <hi>ſtayes,</hi> which <hi>ſtops him,</hi> and <hi>bounds his habitation</hi> that <hi>he</hi> may return to <hi>him</hi> from whom <hi>he is</hi> gone, and <hi>feel after God,</hi> whom <hi>he</hi> hath <hi>loſt,</hi> and <hi>find him whoſe off-ſpring he is,</hi> who is not <hi>very far from him,</hi> though <hi>he be very far from God,</hi> and <hi>alienated by reaſon of wicked works,</hi> for <hi>in him he lives, moves, and hath his being,</hi> muſt needs be truth.</p>
            <p>So, then, unleſſe <hi>ye</hi> will offer violence to the <hi>very</hi> principles of <hi>your</hi> own profeſſions, to the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and to the <hi>witneſſe</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>you</hi> all, <hi>ye</hi> cannot <hi>any</hi> longer oppoſe the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>you (now</hi>)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29826:10"/> made manifeſt, for no <hi>new</hi> thing have <hi>I held</hi> forth to <hi>you,</hi> but that which <hi>was in the beginning,</hi> and which (as <hi>ye</hi> ſee) is the <hi>very</hi> bottom, and foundation of <hi>your</hi> Principles, though <hi>it</hi> be (<hi>newly</hi>) manifeſted, even <hi>the Myſtery which hath been hid from ages, and from generations, but is now made manifeſt to his Saints, to whom God would make known, what is the riches of the Glory of this Myſterie among the Gentiles, which is Chriſt in you, the hope of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, my <hi>dear</hi> friends, be <hi>cool</hi> and <hi>conſiderate,</hi> let <hi>Wiſdom</hi> weigh <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>diſcretion</hi> hold the <hi>ballance</hi> in <hi>your</hi> hearts. Be not <hi>raſh</hi> to judge <hi>that</hi> which <hi>ye</hi> know not, and caſt not <hi>preſently</hi> away that <hi>which ye</hi> do not underſtand, and which may ſeem <hi>croſſe</hi> to the <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> of <hi>what ye</hi> profeſſe, but come to the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>you, Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Light of the World, the true Light that lighteth every man that cometh into the World,</hi> the <hi>meaſure</hi> of <hi>him</hi> in <hi>you,</hi> which <hi>ye have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> And <hi>in</hi> and <hi>with</hi> that <hi>try all things,</hi> and as <hi>ye</hi> find what <hi>I</hi> ſay, anſwering to <hi>that</hi> Principle in <hi>you, ſo do.</hi> And, <hi>the God of Peace, who brought again from the Dead our Lord Jeſus, the great Shepherd of the ſheep through the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> ſhew <hi>you</hi> mercy.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Briſtol</hi> 
                  <date>the 27th. 2d. Moneth 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Geo. Biſhop.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 4. line 11. read hath for having, p. 5. l. 31. blot out of, p. 6. l. 30. blot out in before one, p. 8. l. 19. read Chriſtopherus for Chriſtopher, l. 33. r. good for God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29826:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
